<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Asko Nivala</title>
    <link>https://askonivala.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Asko Nivala</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://askonivala.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Artificial Intelligence Before Computers: The History of Romantic Computationalism</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/projects/aicom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/projects/aicom/</guid>
      <description>TIAS Collegium Fellow 2022–2025
Machine learning and neural networks have developed significantly during the twenty-first century. Despite the success of weak artificial intelligence, strong AI – the creation of an artificial consciousness comparable with humans – is still as much science fiction as it was when Mary Shelley published Frankenstein (1818). My TIAS project Artificial Intelligence Before Computers (AICOM, 2022–20225) explores the history of AI discourse before the invention of the electronic computer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using word vector models to trace conceptual change over time and space in historical newspapers, 1840–1914</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/shico/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/shico/</guid>
      <description>Linking large digitized newspaper corpora in different languages that have become available in national and state libraries opens up new possibilities for the computational analysis of patterns of information flow across national and linguistic boundaries. The significant contribution this article presents is to demonstrate how word vector models can be used to explore the way concepts have shifted in meaning over time, as they migrated across space, by comparing newspapers from different countries published between 1840 and 1914.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atlas of Finnish Literature 1870–1940</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/projects/atlas/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/projects/atlas/</guid>
      <description>Project website (in Finnish) PI: Asko Nivala What kind of geographical areas have been imagined in Finnish literature? What kind of maps do the classics of our literature draw? Where are the centres and peripheries of Finnish literature? Literary cartography emerged in the late 1990s as part of the spatial turn in the humanities. In the 2000s, it has adopted the methods of digital humanities, combining the processing of natural languages with geographic information system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friedrich Schlegel and the Mystical Kingdom of God</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/mystik/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/mystik/</guid>
      <description>Asko Nivala: ”Friedrich Schlegel and the Mystical Kingdom of God.” Mystik und Romantik. Eds. Günther Bonheim, Thomas Isermann &amp;amp; Thomas Regehly. Brill, Leiden 2021, 69–88.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cityscapes and Landscapes in British and German Romanticism (1790–1840)</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/talks/pleasures/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/talks/pleasures/</guid>
      <description>The Pleasures of Imagination – Art, Architecture and Aesthetics in 18th Century Europe
The Finnish Society for Eighteenth-Century Studies Conference Helsinki and on Zoom 21–22 October 2021.
Aalto university, Runeberginkatu 14–16 entrance A, 3rd floor.
My paper &amp;ldquo;Cityscapes and Landscapes in British and German Romanticism (1790–1840)&amp;rdquo; will be held on 22 October 2021 at 14.30.
Caspar David Friedrich: Wiesen bei Greifswald (1821/1822). Wikimedia Commons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Finnish Romanticism became Finnish: The Romantic Background of the Kalevala</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/talks/kalevala-unknown/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/talks/kalevala-unknown/</guid>
      <description>Unknown Tongues is a symposium on Romanticism&amp;rsquo;s minor and marginal languages. On 24 September 2021, invited leading scholars will gather online to debate and discuss what a closer study of (trans)national Romanticisms through their languages can bring to Romantic and nineteenth-century studies, and what relevance a recovery of these traditions may have for our sense of the present.
  Organised by Brecht de Groote (Universiteit Gent ⬨ University of Ghent) and Rhys Kaminski-Jones (Prifysgol Cymru y Drindod Dewi Sant ⬨ University of Wales Trinity Saint David).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enlightenment, Revolution, Melancholia</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/enlightenment-revolution-melancholia/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/enlightenment-revolution-melancholia/</guid>
      <description>The chapter concentrates on the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries and analyzes the ambiguous project of the Enlightenment. The eighteenth century has often been depicted as an era of progress, when new scientific inventions were made and disseminated while the middle class gained more economic and political influence. The 1750s was a turning point, however, after which European intellectual history started to show darker shades and a new sceptical attitude to progress arose.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Institut für Maschinelle Sprachverarbeitung</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/visits/stuttgart/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/visits/stuttgart/</guid>
      <description>In 2020, I was a visiting scholar at the Institut für Maschinelle Sprachverarbeitung (Universität Stuttgart, Germany). During my postdoc at Stuttgart I have not only familiarised myself with the cutting-edge methods of natural language processing (NLP) and machine learning, but also learned good practices of software development like testing and profiling Python code.
Tübingen is not far from Stuttgart and it was possible to see Tübinger Stift, where Hegel, Hölderlin and Schelling studied and visit Hölderlinturm, where Friedrich Hölderlin once lived.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The reuse of texts in Finnish newspapers and journals, 1771–1920</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/historical_methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/historical_methods/</guid>
      <description>The digital collections of newspapers have given rise to a growing interest in studying them with computational methods. This article contributes to this discussion by presenting a method for detecting text reuse in a large corpus of digitized texts. Empirically, the article is based on the corpus of newspapers and journals from the collection of the National Library of Finland. Often, digitized repositories offer only partial views of what actually was published in printed form.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spreading News in 1904</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/bobrikov/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/bobrikov/</guid>
      <description>The assassination of Nikolay Bobrikov, the Governor-General of Finland, on 16 June 1904 was a turning point in Finnish history. It was reported in hundreds, if not thousands, of newspapers worldwide. This article follows the spread of that news, particularly its spread over the first week after the assassination. The study draws on the digital newspaper repositories in Australia, Austria, Denmark, Finland, France, Germany, Mexico, Sweden, the Netherlands and the United States.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NULab for Texts, Maps, and Networks</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/visits/boston/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/visits/boston/</guid>
      <description>From August to December 2019, I was a visiting scholar hosted by the NULab for Texts, Maps, and Networks and the Digital Scholarship Group. NULab was part of the Oceanic Exchanges consortium.
The NULab has built significant expertise in many varieties computational humanities work, with colleagues in literary study, history, computer science, and the social sciences all contributing methodological and domain knowledge. Being a postdoc in this research community greatly benefited the cartographical aspects of my ROMCAR project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>History and Virtual Topology</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/topology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/topology/</guid>
      <description>Drawing on a new materialist approach, this article discusses the concepts of the virtual and virtual topology, and their fruitfulness for historians’ empirical work. It starts by following Gilles Deleuze’s argument that the virtual, the transformative potential of the real, has to be distinguished from the possible, which is merely an imagined double of the given world. Embracing this premise, the article shows the potential of virtual topology to shed light on the transformation of a network in the past.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forschungsschwerpunkt Historische Kulturwissenschaften</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/visits/mainz/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/visits/mainz/</guid>
      <description>In 2017, I spend 4 months as a visiting fellow at Forschungsschwerpunkt Historische Kulturwissenschaften (HKW), Johannes Gutenberg-Universität Mainz, Germany. The research visit was part of my 3-years post doc at the Turku Institute for Advanced Studies (TIAS, University of Turku).
My travel costs and accomodation in Mainz were funded by the Kone Foundation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Romantic Idea of the Golden Age in Friedrich Schlegel&#39;s Philosophy of History</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/schlegel-monograph/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/schlegel-monograph/</guid>
      <description>Asko Nivala: The Romantic Idea of the Golden Age in Friedrich Schlegel&amp;rsquo;s Philosophy of History. Routledge, New York 2017, PREVIEW / ORDER.
The nineteenth-century Romantic understanding of history is often confused with the longing for the past Golden Age. In this book, the Romantic idea of Golden Age is seen from a new angle by discussing it in the context of Friedrich Schlegel’s works. Interestingly, Schlegel argued that the concept of a past Golden Age in the beginning of history was itself a product of antiquity, imagined without any historical ground.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Romantic Cartographies</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/projects/romcar/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/projects/romcar/</guid>
      <description>Lived and Imagined Space in English and German Romantic Texts, 1790–1840 PI: Asko Nivala. Academy of Finland Postdoctoral Researcher 2019-2022 Most texts are spatial implying a network of places. This was especially typical of the Romantic era (1790s–1840s) that was characterised by the growing interest in historical and natural sites. Romantic Cartographies is a digital humanities project that provides new interpretations on English and German Romantic texts by focusing on spatiality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational History and the Transformation of Public Discourse in Finland, 1640–1910</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/projects/comhis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/projects/comhis/</guid>
      <description>PI: Prof. Hannu Salmi The consortium Computational History and the Transformation of Public Discourse in Finland, 1640–1910 (funded by the Academy of Finland programme on Digital Humanities, 2016–2019) is based on the cooperation of four partners: The Faculty of Humanities at the University of Helsinki, the Departments of Cultural History and Future Technologies at the University of Turku and the Centre for Preservation and Digitisation of the National Library of Finland.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Catastrophic Revolution and the Rise of Romantic Bildung</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/catastrophic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/catastrophic/</guid>
      <description>Asko Nivala: &amp;ldquo;Catastrophic Revolution and the Rise of Romantic Bildung&amp;rdquo;, Travelling Notions of Culture in Early Nineteenth-Century Europe. Eds. Hannu Salmi, Asko Nivala, Jukka Sarjala. Routledge, New York 2015, pp. 19-37, PREVIEW / ORDER.
I discuss the rise of Romantic &amp;lsquo;Bildung&amp;rsquo; at the turn of the nineteenth century with a special emphasis on Friedrich Schlegel, but referring also to other famous Romantics such as William Wordsworth and Novalis (Friedrich von Hardenberg, 1772–1801).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Travelling Notions of Culture in Early Nineteenth-Century Europe</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/travelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/publications/travelling/</guid>
      <description>Hannu Salmi, Asko Nivala, Jukka Sarjala (eds.): Travelling Notions of Culture in Early Nineteenth-Century Europe. Routledge, New York 2015, PREVIEW / ORDER.
The notions of culture and civilization are at the heart of European self-image. This book focuses on how space and spatiality contributed to defining the concepts of culture and civilization and, conversely, what kind of spatial ramifications &amp;lsquo;culture&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;civilization&amp;rsquo; entailed. These questions have vital importance to the understanding of this formative period of modern Europe.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Golden Age in Friedrich Schlegel’s Philosophy of History</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/projects/schlegel/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/projects/schlegel/</guid>
      <description>PI: Asko Nivala I defended my doctoral dissertation in 2015. It discussed the themes of the Golden Age and the Kingdom of God in Friedrich Schlegel’s (1772–1829) early thought. The project was funded by the Finnish Cultural Foundation and the Oskar Öflund Foundation. In the final stages of the research work, I was also working in the Travelling Notions of Culture project, funded by the Academy of Finland.
A monograph based on my PhD dissertation was published in February 2017 with the title The Romantic Idea of the Golden Age in Friedrich Schlegel’s Philosophy of History.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Travelling Notions of Culture</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/projects/travelling_project/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/projects/travelling_project/</guid>
      <description>PI: Prof. Hannu Salmi The project Travelling Notions of Culture, funded by the Academy of Finland 2012–2016 and supervised by Prof. Hannu Salmi, studied the changing notions of culture by asking how spatial imagination contributed to defining the concepts of culture and civilisation in early nineteenth-century Europe.
The research results of the project were published in the edited collection Travelling Notions of Culture in Early Nineteenth-Century Europe. Eds. Hannu Salmi, Asko Nivala, Jukka Sarjala.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aboagora</title>
      <link>https://askonivala.github.io/projects/aboagora/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://askonivala.github.io/projects/aboagora/</guid>
      <description>In 2012–2013, I was working as the coordinator of Aboagora: Between Arts and Sciences and was responsible for the organisation of the multidisciplinary Aboagora symposium together with the organisational committee.
Aboagora 2013: The Human Machine Abogora 2013: The Human Machine was organised on August 13-15 and focused on the complex relationships between man and machine. The keynote speakers were Bruce Sterling, Kevin Warwick, Mia Consalvo and Timo Airaksinen.
Aboagora 2012: The Power of the Sacred and the Secular Abogora 2012: The Power of the Sacred and the Secular was held on August 14-16.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
