<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Asko Nivala on Asko Nivala</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Asko Nivala on Asko Nivala</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Asko Nivala</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>History and Virtual Topology: The Nineteenth-Century Press as Material Flow</title>
      <link>/publication/historein/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/historein/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Birth of Homeopathy out of the Spirit of Romanticism / Literature and the Cult of Personality: Essays on Goethe and His Influence / E.T.A. Hoffmann’s Orient: Romantic Aesthetics and the German Imagination</title>
      <link>/publication/err/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/err/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In lieu of an abstract, here is a brief excerpt of the content:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Birth of Homeopathy out of the Spirit of Romanticism&lt;/em&gt;, by Alice A. Kuzniar, Toronto, U of Toronto P, 2017, x + 223 pp., 4
illustrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Literature and the Cult of Personality: Essays on Goethe and His Influence&lt;/em&gt;, by Gregory Maertz, Stuttgart, ibidem,
2017, x + 278 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;E.T.A. Hoffmann’s Orient: Romantic Aesthetics and the German Imagination&lt;/em&gt;, by Joanna Neilly, Cambridge, Legenda,
2016, xii + 157 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asko Nivala&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three monographs under review here relate to German Romanticism and its Anglophone reception. The first book, Alice A. Kuzniar’s
&lt;em&gt;The Birth of Homeopathy out of the Spirit of Romanticism&lt;/em&gt; (2017), surveys the connections between the Romantic philosophy of nature
and the development of homeopathy. The second book, Gregory Maertz’s &lt;em&gt;Literature and the Cult of Personality: Essays on Goethe and
His Influence&lt;/em&gt; (2017), concerns the Anglophone reception of Johann Wolfgang von Goethe (1749–1832) in the United Kingdom and New
England. Finally, &lt;em&gt;E.T.A. Hoffmann’s Orient: Romantic Aesthetics and the German Imagination&lt;/em&gt; (2016) by Joanna Neilly is an intriguing
study of orientalism in the &lt;em&gt;oeuvre&lt;/em&gt; of E. T. A. Hoffmann (1776–1822). As these laudable studies show, Anglophone research on German
Romanticism is an active field of study, producing notable results and making German culture and literature more approachable for an
English-speaking audience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In the Extreme Arctic Wilderness: Polar Regions in Romanticism</title>
      <link>/talk/tromssa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/tromssa/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schillers Geschichtsdenken: Die Unbegreiflichkeit der Weltgeschichte by Alexander Jakovljević (review)</title>
      <link>/publication/schiller/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/schiller/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In lieu of an abstract, here is a brief excerpt of the content:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asko Nivala&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander Jakovljević. &lt;em&gt;Schillers Geschichtsdenken: Die Unbegreiflichkeit der Weltgeschichte&lt;/em&gt;. Berlin:
Ripperger &amp;amp; Kremers Verlag, 2015. 381 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the many contributions of Immanuel Kant&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Critique of Judgment&lt;/em&gt; (1790) was to question the dogmatic
belief in providence: Kant argued that the human mind represents both organic nature and human history as
if (&lt;em&gt;als ob&lt;/em&gt;) both were teleological, although we can never verify this claim. Despite the fact that Kant
limited teleology to regulative use, Karl Löwith claimed in his influential study &lt;em&gt;Meaning in History&lt;/em&gt; (1949)
that the nineteenth-century philosophy of history is nothing but secularized eschatology. Although Löwith&amp;rsquo;s
argument is a simplification, his criticism of master narratives had enormous influence on the development
of postmodernism. Since Hayden White&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Metahistory&lt;/em&gt; (1973), historians have debated to what extent
historical events themselves have order and to what extent it is only the historian&amp;rsquo;s narration that gives
them meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander Jakovljević&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Schillers Geschichtsdenken: Die Unbegreiflichkeit der Weltgeschichte&lt;/em&gt; (2015) shows
how complex Friedrich Schiller&amp;rsquo;s historical thought was, and provides some new insights into how he
theorized the relationship between teleology and contingency in history. Schiller&amp;rsquo;s place is very
interesting among the post-Kantian philosophers, because he published his major works before the rise of
German idealism: his position seems to be somewhere between Kant&amp;rsquo;s regulative approach to teleology and
Hegel&amp;rsquo;s belief that the telos of history is the accumulation of freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jakovljević convincingly shows that Schiller&amp;rsquo;s position is based on the tension between two almost opposite
views of history. In 1789, Schiller was appointed professor of history at the university of Jena on
Goethe&amp;rsquo;s recommendation. His famous inaugural lecture &lt;em&gt;Was heißt und zu welchem Ende studiert man
Universalgeschichte?&lt;/em&gt; (1789) appears to be firmly anchored in the belief that human history is a
teleological process. It was published one year before Kant&amp;rsquo;s criticism of teleological judgments in the
third critique. In contrast, &lt;em&gt;Ueber das Erhabene&lt;/em&gt; (1801) provides a very different understanding of history.
Schiller argued there that history is incomprehensible and seems to be ruled more by coincidence (&lt;em&gt;Zufall&lt;/em&gt;)
than teleology. The previous scholarship has often assumed that Schiller moved from earlier providentialism
to a more pessimist understanding of history because of his disappointment with the horrors of the French
Revolution. According to Jakovljević, Schiller&amp;rsquo;s hovering between providentialism and coincidentalism
should not be seen as a linear development from the former to the latter. Rather Jakovljević proposes that
Schiller&amp;rsquo;s position becomes more understandable in a context of genre-specific readings that take into
account all three fields in which Schiller was active: philosophy of history, historiography, and
historical drama. In addition to the introduction (Chapter 1) and conclusions (Chapter 5), the book is
divided into three chapters that follow this classification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The introduction is carefully written, and defines the key concepts of the study, namely telos, contingency
(&lt;em&gt;Kontingenz&lt;/em&gt;), and coincidence (&lt;em&gt;Zufall&lt;/em&gt;), and explains the theoretical framework provided by Reinhart
Koselleck and Hayden White. Chapter 2 starts with Schiller&amp;rsquo;s inaugural lecture, which again supported the
idea that historical development is teleological. In a teleological framework every historical event must
be necessary, but Schiller&amp;rsquo;s own work as a historian was in tension with this theoretical assumption of
universal history. This problem became evident for Schiller especially when he was working with medieval
sources and the age of Crusades: it was difficult to explain why the Middle Ages were necessary for the
universal development of mankind. Highlighting Schiller&amp;rsquo;s aesthetic approach to history, Jakovljević
focuses on the metaphors Schiller used. For instance, describing medieval history as &amp;ldquo;unknown ocean&amp;rdquo;
(&lt;em&gt;ungewisses Meer&lt;/em&gt;) implies that historical events are coincidental. This difficulty was related to the
premises of the Enlightenment, for the Middle Ages was still mostly seen as an era of religious fanaticism,
political despotism, and a multitude of chaotic events resulting from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[The end of excerpt.]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oceanic Exchanges: Tracing Global Information Networks In Historical Newspaper Repositories, 1840-1914</title>
      <link>/talk/dhn-ocex-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 12:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/dhn-ocex-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Poster at DHN 2018 conference&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presenters: Hannu Salmi, Asko Nivala, Mila Oiva, Otto Latva – Cultural History, University of Turku&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oceanic Exchanges: Tracing Global Information Networks in Historical Newspaper Repositories, 1840-1914&lt;/em&gt; (OcEx) is a &lt;em&gt;Digging into
Data – Transatlantic Platform&lt;/em&gt; funded international and interdisciplinary project with a focus on studying spreading of news globally
in the nineteenth century newspapers. The project combines digitized newspapers from Europe, US, Mexico, Australia, New Zealand, and
the British and Dutch colonies of that time all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project examines patterns of information flow, spread of text reuse, and global conceptual changes across national, cultural and
linguistic boundaries in the nineteenth century newspapers. The project links the different newspaper corpora, scattered into
different national libraries and collections using various kinds of metadata and printed in several languages, into one whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research group members come from Finland, the US, the Netherlands, Germany, Mexico, and UK. OcEx’s participating institutions are
Loughborough University, Northeastern University, North Carolina State University, Universität Stuttgart, Universidad Nacional
Autónoma de México, University College London, University of Nebraska-Lincoln, University of Turku, and Utrecht University. The
project’s 90 million newspaper pages come from Australia&amp;rsquo;s Trove Newspapers, the British Newspapers Archive, Chronicling America
(US), Europeana Newspapers, Hemeroteca Nacional Digital de México, National Library of Finland, National Library of the Netherlands
(KB), the National Library of Wales, New Zealand’s PapersPast, and a strategic collaboration with Cengage Publishing, one of the
leading commercial custodians of digitized newspapers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metadata Analysis and Text Reuse Detection: Reassessing public discourse in Finland through newspapers and journals 1771–1917</title>
      <link>/talk/dhn-comhis-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/dhn-comhis-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Poster at DHN 2018 conference&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presenters: Ginter, Filip (1); Kanner, Antti (2); Lahti, Leo (1); Marjanen, Jani (2); Mäkelä, Eetu (2); Nivala, Asko (1); Rantala, Heli (1); Salmi, Hannu (1); Sippola, Reetta (1); Tolonen, Mikko (2); Vaara, Ville (2); Vesanto, Aleksi (2)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisation(s): 1: University of Turku; 2: University of Helsinki&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the period 1771–1917 newspapers developed as a mass medium in the Grand Duchy of Finland. This happened within two different imperial configurations (Sweden until 1809 and Russia 1809–1917) and in two main languages – Swedish and Finnish. &lt;em&gt;The Computational History and the Transformation of Public Discourse in Finland, 1640–1910&lt;/em&gt; (COMHIS) project studies the transformation of public discourse in Europe and in Finland via an innovative combination of original data, state-of-the-art quantitative methods that have not been previously applied in this context, and an open source collaboration model.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Redefinition of European Borders in English and German Romanticism</title>
      <link>/talk/sks/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/sks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most texts are spatial implying a network of important places. This was especially typical of the Romantic era (1790–1840) that was characterised by the growing interest in historical and natural sites. My research project provides a new interpretation of English and German Romanticism by changing the focus from temporal to spatial. On the special focus of this presentation is Romantic Philhellenism and the interest in the Greek areas of the Ottoman Empire. The Napoleonic Wars (1803–1815) and the Greek War of Independence (1821–1829) were redefining the borders of Europe, and the English and German Romantics were actively participating on the spatial definition of European culture. I analyse the spatiality of Romantic texts by reconstructing the various maps they implied by using named-entity recognition (NER), geoparsing and other text mining methods. The study of Romanticism has often focused on the canon of few famous authors, but applying the methods of the digital humanities has a potential to analyse a much bigger corpus of primary sources.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review of Romanticism, Humanism, Judaism / Romantik, Humanismus, Judentum</title>
      <link>/publication/eichner/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/eichner/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friedrich Schlegel and Ancient Greece as the Golden Age</title>
      <link>/talk/athens/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/athens/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The nineteenth-century Romantic understanding of history is often confused with the longing for the past Golden Age. In this paper — that is based on my forth-coming monograph &lt;em&gt;The Romantic Idea of the Golden Age in Friedrich Schlegel’s Philosophy of History&lt;/em&gt; (New York: Routledge 2017) — the problem of the Golden Age is seen from a new angle by discussing it in the context of Friedrich Schlegel’s studies on ancient Greece. Interestingly, Schlegel argued that Hesiod’s myth of a past Golden Age in the beginning of history was itself a product of antiquity, imagined without any historical ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By making a distinction between ‘the Golden Age’ and ‘the age of blossoming’ (Blütezeit) the paper shows that Schlegel was not a primitivist and he was in fact very skeptical about the Golden Age in the beginning of time. Schlegel compared the history of antiquity with the growth of a plant, seeing the highest phase of Greek civilization in Attic culture (rather than in the ‘savage’ world of Homer’s epics), and its final urban stage in Alexandria represented decay. The status of ancient Athens was, in Schlegel’s view, the fullest flowering of Western civilization. In contrast to Winckelmann’s studies on sculpture, Schlegel located the core of the Greek cultivation in its institution of the theatre. Attic tragedy, and more specifically Sophocles, represented the apogee of the natural cultivation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Repeatable results</title>
      <link>/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 14:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;In 2014—2017, my blog was based on &lt;a href=&#34;http://jekyllrb.com&#34;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, which was a logical choice because I host it on GitHub pages. Now I have moved to Hugo. This is because of &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34;&gt;Blogdown&lt;/a&gt; and its support for R Markdown. My earlier site was also based on Markdown. However, R Markdown enables one not only to cite program code, but to execute it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little bit similarly as Jupyter Notebook, R Markdown makes it possible to run code on a static HTML page. For example, I will write a very simple R function and its output will be shown under the source code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;curve(x^2, from=1, to=50, , xlab=&amp;quot;x&amp;quot;, ylab=&amp;quot;y&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt; This is probably insignificant for a common blogger, but R Markdown might be a fundamental step for the DH community. The humanists seldom consider the repeatability of their results, because hermeneutical interpretations are — to some extent — &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt; conclusions. In contrast to that, the results of algorithmic methods should be repeatable in principle. R Markdown enables the scholar to make the stages of her research process transparent, which could be also a great pedagogical asset.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Romantic Cartographies</title>
      <link>/project/cartography/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/cartography/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;romantic-cartographies-lived-and-imagined-space-in-english-and-german-romantic-texts-1790-1840&#34;&gt;Romantic Cartographies: Lived and Imagined Space in English and German Romantic Texts, 1790–1840&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most texts are spatial implying a network of important places. This was especially typical of the Romantic era (1790–1840) that was characterised by the growing interest in historical and natural sites. My postdoctoral research project provides a new interpretation of English and German Romanticism by changing the focus from temporal to spatial. I analyse the spatiality of Romantic texts by reconstructing the various geographic maps they implied. My specific focus is on the tension between metropolises, small towns, countryside and historical sites. The project transcends the narrow focus on single Romantic author, analysing a big textual corpus digitally in addition to close reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My primary sources consist of a representative corpus of English and German Romantic texts including canonical works but also texts by women, minority and non-canonical authors. The most popular genres of Romanticism were novel and lyric poetry; but also essays, biographies, literary criticism, travelogues and historiography are included in the corpus. The metadata abstracted from correspondence is used to build another database to enable comparison between fictive and actual geographic maps of Romantic spatiality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project focuses thematically on the destabilisation of the centre-periphery distinction during the Romanticism and it has three main objectives. First, building a database of place names mentioned in the primary sources and visualise them on historical maps. I will apply existing geoparsing algorithms and also write a new Python programme called Strabo for this. The resulting database will be then published as an interactive website open for other scholars and general public. The second objective is to develop a research methodology for classifying place names and embedding geographical locations with emotional and cognitive judgements. The aim of this objective is to avoid the reduction of the lived space to a Cartesian coordinate grid, typical of the spatial humanities projects. The third objective is using the spatial database as a heuristic device for finding the relevant text passages for close reading.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A System for Identifying and Exploring Text Repetition in Large Historical Document Corpora</title>
      <link>/publication/system/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/system/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applying BLAST to Text Reuse Detection in Finnish Newspapers and Journals, 1771–1910</title>
      <link>/publication/blast/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/blast/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friedrich Schlegel&#39;s Philosophy of History (2007—2015)</title>
      <link>/project/schlegel/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/schlegel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I defended my doctoral dissertation in 2015. It discussed the themes of the Golden Age and the Kingdom of God in Friedrich Schlegel’s (1772–1829) early thought. The project was funded by the Finnish Cultural Foundation and the Oskar Öflund Foundation. In the final stages of the research work, I was also working in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.utu.fi/fi/yksikot/hum/yksikot/kulttuurihistoria/tutkimus/Sivut/travelling_notions_of_culture.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Travelling Notions of Culture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; project, funded by the Academy of Finland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A monograph based on my PhD dissertation was published in February 2017 with the title &lt;a href=&#34;/publication/schlegel-monograph/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Romantic Idea of the Golden Age in Friedrich Schlegel’s Philosophy of History&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In addition to that, I have published many research articles about Friedrich Schlegel.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COMHIS</title>
      <link>/project/comhis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/comhis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
