<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Asko Nivala on Asko Nivala</title>
    <link>http://askonivala.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Asko Nivala on Asko Nivala</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Asko Nivala</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>In the Extreme Arctic Wilderness: Polar Regions in Romanticism</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/tromssa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/tromssa/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Redefinition of European Borders in English and German Romanticism</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/sks/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/sks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most texts are spatial implying a network of important places. This was especially typical of the Romantic era (1790–1840) that was characterised by the growing interest in historical and natural sites. My research project provides a new interpretation of English and German Romanticism by changing the focus from temporal to spatial. On the special focus of this presentation is Romantic Philhellenism and the interest in the Greek areas of the Ottoman Empire. The Napoleonic Wars (1803–1815) and the Greek War of Independence (1821–1829) were redefining the borders of Europe, and the English and German Romantics were actively participating on the spatial definition of European culture. I analyse the spatiality of Romantic texts by reconstructing the various maps they implied by using named-entity recognition (NER), geoparsing and other text mining methods. The study of Romanticism has often focused on the canon of few famous authors, but applying the methods of the digital humanities has a potential to analyse a much bigger corpus of primary sources.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review of Romanticism, Humanism, Judaism / Romantik, Humanismus, Judentum</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/eichner/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/eichner/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friedrich Schlegel and Ancient Greece as the Golden Age</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/athens/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/athens/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The nineteenth-century Romantic understanding of history is often confused with the longing for the past Golden Age. In this paper — that is based on my forth-coming monograph &lt;em&gt;The Romantic Idea of the Golden Age in Friedrich Schlegel’s Philosophy of History&lt;/em&gt; (New York: Routledge 2017) — the problem of the Golden Age is seen from a new angle by discussing it in the context of Friedrich Schlegel’s studies on ancient Greece. Interestingly, Schlegel argued that Hesiod’s myth of a past Golden Age in the beginning of history was itself a product of antiquity, imagined without any historical ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By making a distinction between ‘the Golden Age’ and ‘the age of blossoming’ (Blütezeit) the paper shows that Schlegel was not a primitivist and he was in fact very skeptical about the Golden Age in the beginning of time. Schlegel compared the history of antiquity with the growth of a plant, seeing the highest phase of Greek civilization in Attic culture (rather than in the ‘savage’ world of Homer’s epics), and its final urban stage in Alexandria represented decay. The status of ancient Athens was, in Schlegel’s view, the fullest flowering of Western civilization. In contrast to Winckelmann’s studies on sculpture, Schlegel located the core of the Greek cultivation in its institution of the theatre. Attic tragedy, and more specifically Sophocles, represented the apogee of the natural cultivation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Repeatable results</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 14:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2014—2017, my blog was based on &lt;a href=&#34;http://jekyllrb.com&#34;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, which was a logical choice because I host it on GitHub pages. Now I have moved to Hugo. This is because of &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34;&gt;Blogdown&lt;/a&gt; and its support for R Markdown. My earlier site was also based on Markdown. However, R Markdown enables one not only to cite program code, but to execute it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little bit similarly as Jupyter Notebook, R Markdown makes it possible to run code on a static HTML page. For example, I will write a very simple R function and its output will be shown under the source code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;curve(x^2, from=1, to=50, , xlab=&amp;quot;x&amp;quot;, ylab=&amp;quot;y&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://askonivala.github.io/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;
This is probably insignificant for a common blogger, but R Markdown might be a fundamental step for the DH community. The humanists seldom consider the repeatability of their results, because hermeneutical interpretations are — to some extent — &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt; conclusions. In contrast to that, the results of algorithmic methods should be repeatable in principle. R Markdown enables the scholar to make the stages of her research process transparent, which could be also a great pedagogical asset.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Romantic Cartographies</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/project/cartography/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/project/cartography/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;romantic-cartographies-lived-and-imagined-space-in-english-and-german-romantic-texts-1790-1840&#34;&gt;Romantic Cartographies: Lived and Imagined Space in English and German Romantic Texts, 1790–1840&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most texts are spatial implying a network of important places. This was especially typical of the Romantic era (1790–1840) that was characterised by the growing interest in historical and natural sites. My postdoctoral research project provides a new interpretation of English and German Romanticism by changing the focus from temporal to spatial. I analyse the spatiality of Romantic texts by reconstructing the various geographic maps they implied. My specific focus is on the tension between metropolises, small towns, countryside and historical sites. The project transcends the narrow focus on single Romantic author, analysing a big textual corpus digitally in addition to close reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My primary sources consist of a representative corpus of English and German Romantic texts including canonical works but also texts by women, minority and non-canonical authors. The most popular genres of Romanticism were novel and lyric poetry; but also essays, biographies, literary criticism, travelogues and historiography are included in the corpus. The metadata abstracted from correspondence is used to build another database to enable comparison between fictive and actual geographic maps of Romantic spatiality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project focuses thematically on the destabilisation of the centre-periphery distinction during the Romanticism and it has three main objectives. First, building a database of place names mentioned in the primary sources and visualise them on historical maps. I will apply existing geoparsing algorithms and also write a new Python programme called Strabo for this. The resulting database will be then published as an interactive website open for other scholars and general public. The second objective is to develop a research methodology for classifying place names and embedding geographical locations with emotional and cognitive judgements. The aim of this objective is to avoid the reduction of the lived space to a Cartesian coordinate grid, typical of the spatial humanities projects. The third objective is using the spatial database as a heuristic device for finding the relevant text passages for close reading.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A System for Identifying and Exploring Text Repetition in Large Historical Document Corpora</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/system/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/system/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applying BLAST to Text Reuse Detection in Finnish Newspapers and Journals, 1771–1910</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/blast/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/blast/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friedrich Schlegel&#39;s Philosophy of History (2007—2015)</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/project/schlegel/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/project/schlegel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I defended my doctoral dissertation in 2015. It discussed the themes of the Golden Age and the Kingdom of God in Friedrich Schlegel’s (1772–1829) early thought. The project was funded by the Finnish Cultural Foundation and the Oskar Öflund Foundation. In the final stages of the research work, I was also working in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.utu.fi/fi/yksikot/hum/yksikot/kulttuurihistoria/tutkimus/Sivut/travelling_notions_of_culture.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Travelling Notions of Culture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; project, funded by the Academy of Finland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A monograph based on my PhD dissertation was published in February 2017 with the title &lt;a href=&#34;http://askonivala.github.io/publication/schlegel-monograph/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Romantic Idea of the Golden Age in Friedrich Schlegel’s Philosophy of History&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In addition to that, I have published many research articles about Friedrich Schlegel.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COMHIS</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/project/comhis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/project/comhis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Travelling Notions of Culture</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/project/travelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/project/travelling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Romantic Idea of the Golden Age in Friedrich Schlegel&#39;s Philosophy of History</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/schlegel-monograph/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/schlegel-monograph/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Asko Nivalas Arbeit ist von Bedeutung für die Friedrich-Schlegel-Forschung aufgrund ihrer neuen Einsichten in ein zentrales Konzept
seiner Geschichtsphilosophie. Sie überzeugt durch ihren Mut zur Komplexität. Zugleich liegt ein Verdienst der Dissertation darin, der
englischsprachigen Forschung eine Einführung in Schlegels Denken zu bieten. Das leistet die Arbeit durch den Ausweis von
Anknüpfungspunkten an aktuelle theoretische Diskurse (›posthumanism‹, ›ecocriticism‹, ›primitivism‹) auf der einen Seite und auf der
anderen durch ein hohes Reflexionsniveau hinsichtlich der Übersetzung zentraler Termini Schlegels ins Englische.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Elisa Ronzheimer, Athenäum – &lt;em&gt;Jahrbuch der Friedrich Schlegel-Gesellschaft&lt;/em&gt; 2017&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Of Mice and Machines: Posthumanist Reading of E. T. A. Hoffmann&#39;s Nutcracker and the Mouse King</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/colorado/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/colorado/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;E. T. A. Hoffmann’s “Nutcracker and the Mouse King” (“Nussknacker und Mausekönig”, 1816) is among the most read Romantic fairy tales. Despite, its automaton motif has not been discussed a lot. My paper provides a posthumanist reading of the text in comparison with “The Sandman” (“Der Sandman”, 1817) that includes the famous female automaton Olimpia. As the title suggests, “Nutcracker and the Mouse King” juxtaposes the machine with the organism. The story happens on the Christmas, when two children, Marie and Fritz, are waiting for their presents. The engineer Drosselmeyer gives them a mechanical castle, which is so immersive that Fritz tries to go inside its mechanism. However, children lose soon their interest in the castle, because it can only operate on the pregiven rules of the machinery. At the first glance, Hoffmann seems to juxtapose the mechanical castle with the free imagination of children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially interesting are the similarities between Marie’s godfather Drosselmeier and Coppelius in “The Sandman”: both are engineers of automata. One of the most horrible scenes in “The Sandman” is Coppelius disassembling Nathanael’s body. Although “Nutcracker and the Mouse King” is a fairy tale, also Drosselmeier restructures Princess Pirlipat’s body like an automaton: “He took Princess Pirlipat very carefully to pieces, screwed off her hands and her feet, and examined her interior structure.” In a posthumanist way, “The Nutcracker and the Mouse King” questions any simple boundary between an animal and a machine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Romantic Anthropocene? The Nonhuman Agency of the Polar Regions in Romanticism</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/geneva/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/geneva/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I delivered a paper “The Romantic Anthropocene? The Nonhuman Agency of the Polar Regions in Romanticism” in &lt;em&gt;Encountering Materiality: Science, Art, Language&lt;/em&gt; conference in Geneva, 23 – 25 June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://askonivala.github.io/img/frankenstein.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Frankenstein&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The special focus of my talk was Mary Shelley’s Frankenstein, and many key scenes of the novel are located in Geneva. Even the conference venue was very close to the Plainpalais, where Victor Frankenstein’s brother, William, is murdered in the novel. There is now a bronze statue of the Creature in the murder place and he is looking towards the Salève, where he will hide after his deed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mediality and Intermediality in Friedrich Schlegel’s Early Romantic Thought</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/intermediality/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/intermediality/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
