<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2 on Asko Nivala</title>
    <link>/publication_types/2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2 on Asko Nivala</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Asko Nivala</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/publication_types/2/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Birth of Homeopathy out of the Spirit of Romanticism / Literature and the Cult of Personality: Essays on Goethe and His Influence / E.T.A. Hoffmann’s Orient: Romantic Aesthetics and the German Imagination</title>
      <link>/publication/err/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/err/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In lieu of an abstract, here is a brief excerpt of the content:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Birth of Homeopathy out of the Spirit of Romanticism&lt;/em&gt;, by Alice A. Kuzniar, Toronto, U of Toronto P, 2017, x + 223 pp., 4
illustrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Literature and the Cult of Personality: Essays on Goethe and His Influence&lt;/em&gt;, by Gregory Maertz, Stuttgart, ibidem,
2017, x + 278 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;E.T.A. Hoffmann’s Orient: Romantic Aesthetics and the German Imagination&lt;/em&gt;, by Joanna Neilly, Cambridge, Legenda,
2016, xii + 157 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asko Nivala&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three monographs under review here relate to German Romanticism and its Anglophone reception. The first book, Alice A. Kuzniar’s
&lt;em&gt;The Birth of Homeopathy out of the Spirit of Romanticism&lt;/em&gt; (2017), surveys the connections between the Romantic philosophy of nature
and the development of homeopathy. The second book, Gregory Maertz’s &lt;em&gt;Literature and the Cult of Personality: Essays on Goethe and
His Influence&lt;/em&gt; (2017), concerns the Anglophone reception of Johann Wolfgang von Goethe (1749–1832) in the United Kingdom and New
England. Finally, &lt;em&gt;E.T.A. Hoffmann’s Orient: Romantic Aesthetics and the German Imagination&lt;/em&gt; (2016) by Joanna Neilly is an intriguing
study of orientalism in the &lt;em&gt;oeuvre&lt;/em&gt; of E. T. A. Hoffmann (1776–1822). As these laudable studies show, Anglophone research on German
Romanticism is an active field of study, producing notable results and making German culture and literature more approachable for an
English-speaking audience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schillers Geschichtsdenken: Die Unbegreiflichkeit der Weltgeschichte by Alexander Jakovljević (review)</title>
      <link>/publication/schiller/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/schiller/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In lieu of an abstract, here is a brief excerpt of the content:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asko Nivala&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander Jakovljević. &lt;em&gt;Schillers Geschichtsdenken: Die Unbegreiflichkeit der Weltgeschichte&lt;/em&gt;. Berlin:
Ripperger &amp;amp; Kremers Verlag, 2015. 381 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the many contributions of Immanuel Kant&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Critique of Judgment&lt;/em&gt; (1790) was to question the dogmatic
belief in providence: Kant argued that the human mind represents both organic nature and human history as
if (&lt;em&gt;als ob&lt;/em&gt;) both were teleological, although we can never verify this claim. Despite the fact that Kant
limited teleology to regulative use, Karl Löwith claimed in his influential study &lt;em&gt;Meaning in History&lt;/em&gt; (1949)
that the nineteenth-century philosophy of history is nothing but secularized eschatology. Although Löwith&amp;rsquo;s
argument is a simplification, his criticism of master narratives had enormous influence on the development
of postmodernism. Since Hayden White&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Metahistory&lt;/em&gt; (1973), historians have debated to what extent
historical events themselves have order and to what extent it is only the historian&amp;rsquo;s narration that gives
them meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander Jakovljević&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Schillers Geschichtsdenken: Die Unbegreiflichkeit der Weltgeschichte&lt;/em&gt; (2015) shows
how complex Friedrich Schiller&amp;rsquo;s historical thought was, and provides some new insights into how he
theorized the relationship between teleology and contingency in history. Schiller&amp;rsquo;s place is very
interesting among the post-Kantian philosophers, because he published his major works before the rise of
German idealism: his position seems to be somewhere between Kant&amp;rsquo;s regulative approach to teleology and
Hegel&amp;rsquo;s belief that the telos of history is the accumulation of freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jakovljević convincingly shows that Schiller&amp;rsquo;s position is based on the tension between two almost opposite
views of history. In 1789, Schiller was appointed professor of history at the university of Jena on
Goethe&amp;rsquo;s recommendation. His famous inaugural lecture &lt;em&gt;Was heißt und zu welchem Ende studiert man
Universalgeschichte?&lt;/em&gt; (1789) appears to be firmly anchored in the belief that human history is a
teleological process. It was published one year before Kant&amp;rsquo;s criticism of teleological judgments in the
third critique. In contrast, &lt;em&gt;Ueber das Erhabene&lt;/em&gt; (1801) provides a very different understanding of history.
Schiller argued there that history is incomprehensible and seems to be ruled more by coincidence (&lt;em&gt;Zufall&lt;/em&gt;)
than teleology. The previous scholarship has often assumed that Schiller moved from earlier providentialism
to a more pessimist understanding of history because of his disappointment with the horrors of the French
Revolution. According to Jakovljević, Schiller&amp;rsquo;s hovering between providentialism and coincidentalism
should not be seen as a linear development from the former to the latter. Rather Jakovljević proposes that
Schiller&amp;rsquo;s position becomes more understandable in a context of genre-specific readings that take into
account all three fields in which Schiller was active: philosophy of history, historiography, and
historical drama. In addition to the introduction (Chapter 1) and conclusions (Chapter 5), the book is
divided into three chapters that follow this classification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The introduction is carefully written, and defines the key concepts of the study, namely telos, contingency
(&lt;em&gt;Kontingenz&lt;/em&gt;), and coincidence (&lt;em&gt;Zufall&lt;/em&gt;), and explains the theoretical framework provided by Reinhart
Koselleck and Hayden White. Chapter 2 starts with Schiller&amp;rsquo;s inaugural lecture, which again supported the
idea that historical development is teleological. In a teleological framework every historical event must
be necessary, but Schiller&amp;rsquo;s own work as a historian was in tension with this theoretical assumption of
universal history. This problem became evident for Schiller especially when he was working with medieval
sources and the age of Crusades: it was difficult to explain why the Middle Ages were necessary for the
universal development of mankind. Highlighting Schiller&amp;rsquo;s aesthetic approach to history, Jakovljević
focuses on the metaphors Schiller used. For instance, describing medieval history as &amp;ldquo;unknown ocean&amp;rdquo;
(&lt;em&gt;ungewisses Meer&lt;/em&gt;) implies that historical events are coincidental. This difficulty was related to the
premises of the Enlightenment, for the Middle Ages was still mostly seen as an era of religious fanaticism,
political despotism, and a multitude of chaotic events resulting from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[The end of excerpt.]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review of Romanticism, Humanism, Judaism / Romantik, Humanismus, Judentum</title>
      <link>/publication/eichner/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/eichner/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
