<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Asko Nivala on Asko Nivala</title>
    <link>/fi/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Asko Nivala on Asko Nivala</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Asko Nivala</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/fi/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>History and Virtual Topology: The Nineteenth-Century Press as Material Flow</title>
      <link>/fi/publication/historein/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/fi/publication/historein/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Birth of Homeopathy out of the Spirit of Romanticism / Literature and the Cult of Personality: Essays on Goethe and His Influence / E.T.A. Hoffmann’s Orient: Romantic Aesthetics and the German Imagination</title>
      <link>/fi/publication/err/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/fi/publication/err/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In lieu of an abstract, here is a brief excerpt of the content:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Birth of Homeopathy out of the Spirit of Romanticism&lt;/em&gt;, by Alice A. Kuzniar, Toronto, U of Toronto P, 2017, x + 223 pp., 4
illustrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Literature and the Cult of Personality: Essays on Goethe and His Influence&lt;/em&gt;, by Gregory Maertz, Stuttgart, ibidem,
2017, x + 278 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;E.T.A. Hoffmann’s Orient: Romantic Aesthetics and the German Imagination&lt;/em&gt;, by Joanna Neilly, Cambridge, Legenda,
2016, xii + 157 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asko Nivala&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three monographs under review here relate to German Romanticism and its Anglophone reception. The first book, Alice A. Kuzniar’s
&lt;em&gt;The Birth of Homeopathy out of the Spirit of Romanticism&lt;/em&gt; (2017), surveys the connections between the Romantic philosophy of nature
and the development of homeopathy. The second book, Gregory Maertz’s &lt;em&gt;Literature and the Cult of Personality: Essays on Goethe and
His Influence&lt;/em&gt; (2017), concerns the Anglophone reception of Johann Wolfgang von Goethe (1749–1832) in the United Kingdom and New
England. Finally, &lt;em&gt;E.T.A. Hoffmann’s Orient: Romantic Aesthetics and the German Imagination&lt;/em&gt; (2016) by Joanna Neilly is an intriguing
study of orientalism in the &lt;em&gt;oeuvre&lt;/em&gt; of E. T. A. Hoffmann (1776–1822). As these laudable studies show, Anglophone research on German
Romanticism is an active field of study, producing notable results and making German culture and literature more approachable for an
English-speaking audience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schillers Geschichtsdenken: Die Unbegreiflichkeit der Weltgeschichte by Alexander Jakovljević (review)</title>
      <link>/fi/publication/schiller/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/fi/publication/schiller/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In lieu of an abstract, here is a brief excerpt of the content:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asko Nivala&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander Jakovljević. &lt;em&gt;Schillers Geschichtsdenken: Die Unbegreiflichkeit der Weltgeschichte&lt;/em&gt;. Berlin:
Ripperger &amp;amp; Kremers Verlag, 2015. 381 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the many contributions of Immanuel Kant&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Critique of Judgment&lt;/em&gt; (1790) was to question the dogmatic
belief in providence: Kant argued that the human mind represents both organic nature and human history as
if (&lt;em&gt;als ob&lt;/em&gt;) both were teleological, although we can never verify this claim. Despite the fact that Kant
limited teleology to regulative use, Karl Löwith claimed in his influential study &lt;em&gt;Meaning in History&lt;/em&gt; (1949)
that the nineteenth-century philosophy of history is nothing but secularized eschatology. Although Löwith&amp;rsquo;s
argument is a simplification, his criticism of master narratives had enormous influence on the development
of postmodernism. Since Hayden White&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Metahistory&lt;/em&gt; (1973), historians have debated to what extent
historical events themselves have order and to what extent it is only the historian&amp;rsquo;s narration that gives
them meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander Jakovljević&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Schillers Geschichtsdenken: Die Unbegreiflichkeit der Weltgeschichte&lt;/em&gt; (2015) shows
how complex Friedrich Schiller&amp;rsquo;s historical thought was, and provides some new insights into how he
theorized the relationship between teleology and contingency in history. Schiller&amp;rsquo;s place is very
interesting among the post-Kantian philosophers, because he published his major works before the rise of
German idealism: his position seems to be somewhere between Kant&amp;rsquo;s regulative approach to teleology and
Hegel&amp;rsquo;s belief that the telos of history is the accumulation of freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jakovljević convincingly shows that Schiller&amp;rsquo;s position is based on the tension between two almost opposite
views of history. In 1789, Schiller was appointed professor of history at the university of Jena on
Goethe&amp;rsquo;s recommendation. His famous inaugural lecture &lt;em&gt;Was heißt und zu welchem Ende studiert man
Universalgeschichte?&lt;/em&gt; (1789) appears to be firmly anchored in the belief that human history is a
teleological process. It was published one year before Kant&amp;rsquo;s criticism of teleological judgments in the
third critique. In contrast, &lt;em&gt;Ueber das Erhabene&lt;/em&gt; (1801) provides a very different understanding of history.
Schiller argued there that history is incomprehensible and seems to be ruled more by coincidence (&lt;em&gt;Zufall&lt;/em&gt;)
than teleology. The previous scholarship has often assumed that Schiller moved from earlier providentialism
to a more pessimist understanding of history because of his disappointment with the horrors of the French
Revolution. According to Jakovljević, Schiller&amp;rsquo;s hovering between providentialism and coincidentalism
should not be seen as a linear development from the former to the latter. Rather Jakovljević proposes that
Schiller&amp;rsquo;s position becomes more understandable in a context of genre-specific readings that take into
account all three fields in which Schiller was active: philosophy of history, historiography, and
historical drama. In addition to the introduction (Chapter 1) and conclusions (Chapter 5), the book is
divided into three chapters that follow this classification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The introduction is carefully written, and defines the key concepts of the study, namely telos, contingency
(&lt;em&gt;Kontingenz&lt;/em&gt;), and coincidence (&lt;em&gt;Zufall&lt;/em&gt;), and explains the theoretical framework provided by Reinhart
Koselleck and Hayden White. Chapter 2 starts with Schiller&amp;rsquo;s inaugural lecture, which again supported the
idea that historical development is teleological. In a teleological framework every historical event must
be necessary, but Schiller&amp;rsquo;s own work as a historian was in tension with this theoretical assumption of
universal history. This problem became evident for Schiller especially when he was working with medieval
sources and the age of Crusades: it was difficult to explain why the Middle Ages were necessary for the
universal development of mankind. Highlighting Schiller&amp;rsquo;s aesthetic approach to history, Jakovljević
focuses on the metaphors Schiller used. For instance, describing medieval history as &amp;ldquo;unknown ocean&amp;rdquo;
(&lt;em&gt;ungewisses Meer&lt;/em&gt;) implies that historical events are coincidental. This difficulty was related to the
premises of the Enlightenment, for the Middle Ages was still mostly seen as an era of religious fanaticism,
political despotism, and a multitude of chaotic events resulting from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[The end of excerpt.]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Återanvändningen av text i den finska tidningspressen 1771–1853</title>
      <link>/fi/publication/histid/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/fi/publication/histid/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digitaaliset ihmistieteet teemanumero</title>
      <link>/fi/publication/netn-digi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/fi/publication/netn-digi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;s. 63 Asko Nivala, &lt;a href=&#34;https://askonivala.github.io/fi/publication/netn-what-is-digihum/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mitä on digitaalinen humanismi?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;s. 71 Hannu Salmi, Viraalisuus – kulttuurihistoriallinen näkökulma&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;s. 83 Juho Rantala, Uusi intelligentsia ja digitaaliset ihmistieteet – McKenzie Warkin mietteitä&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;s. 86 Reetta Eiranen, Kirjallisuudentutkija, joka haluaa rikkoa kirjan – Laura Mandell ja itsekriittinen ihmistiede&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;s. 89 Asko Nivala, &lt;a href=&#34;https://askonivala.github.io/fi/publication/netn-parikka/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Digitaalisten ihmistieteiden materiaalisesta perustasta – Haastattelussa Jussi Parikka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;s. 95 Maija Paavolainen, Digitaaliset ihmistieteet huipulta huipulle? HELDIG Summitissa&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;s. 97 Risto Turunen, Humanisti, kurkista makroskooppiin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;s. 101 Juho Rantala, Koodin ja ohjelmiston filosofiasta&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digitaalisten ihmistieteiden materiaalisesta perustasta. Haastattelussa Jussi Parikka</title>
      <link>/fi/publication/netn-parikka/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/fi/publication/netn-parikka/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mitä on digitaalinen humanismi?</title>
      <link>/fi/publication/netn-what-is-digihum/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/fi/publication/netn-what-is-digihum/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review of Romanticism, Humanism, Judaism / Romantik, Humanismus, Judentum</title>
      <link>/fi/publication/eichner/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/fi/publication/eichner/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digitaalinen humanismi ja historiatieteet (arvostelu)</title>
      <link>/fi/publication/haik-digi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/fi/publication/haik-digi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutkimuksen toistettavuudesta</title>
      <link>/fi/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 14:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/fi/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Tämä sivusto toimi vuosina 2014—2017 GitHubin käyttämän &lt;a href=&#34;http://jekyllrb.com&#34;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;-tulkin kautta, mutta olen nyt siirtänyt sivut Hugo-alustaan. Syynä muutokseen on &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34;&gt;Blogdown&lt;/a&gt; ja sen tuoma tuki R Markdown -kielelle. Aiempikin sivusto perustui Markdownin kääntämiseen staattisiksi HTML-sivuiksi, mutta R Markdown tuo mukanaan erään mielenkiintoisen lisän: se mahdollistaa ohjelmakoodin siteeraamisen ohella sen suorittamisen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hieman Jupyter Notebookin tavoin R Markdown mahdollistaa ohjelmakoodin ajamisen HTML-sivuilla. Ohessa on varsin yksinkertaisen funktion lähdekoodi ja alle sen suorittamisen tuottama kuvaaja.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;curve(x^2, from=1, to=50, , xlab=&amp;quot;x&amp;quot;, ylab=&amp;quot;y&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown.fi_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asia ei ehkä vaikuta kovin kummoiselta tavallisen blogistin näkökulmasta, mutta digitaalisten ihmistieteiden kannalta R Markdown voi osoittautua vallankumoukselliseksi. Humanistit eivät ole tottuneet ajattelemaan päätelmiensä toistettavuutta, koska hermeneuttiset tulkinnat ovat ainakin jossain määrin &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt; -luonteisia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Algoritmeihin perustuvat menetelmät poikkeavat siinä suhteessa tulkinnoista, että ne ovat lähtökohtaisesti toistettavissa. R Markdown mahdollistaa näin digitaalisen tutkimusprosessin tekemisen askel askeleelta läpinäkyväksi ja toimii samalla myös erinomaisena pedagogisena välineenä.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Romantic Cartographies</title>
      <link>/fi/project/cartography/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/fi/project/cartography/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;romantic-cartographies-lived-and-imagined-space-in-english-and-german-romantic-texts-1790-1840&#34;&gt;Romantic Cartographies: Lived and Imagined Space in English and German Romantic Texts, 1790–1840&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most texts are spatial implying a network of important places. This was especially typical of the Romantic era (1790–1840) that was characterised by the growing interest in historical and natural sites. My postdoctoral research project provides a new interpretation of English and German Romanticism by changing the focus from temporal to spatial. I analyse the spatiality of Romantic texts by reconstructing the various geographic maps they implied. My specific focus is on the tension between metropolises, small towns, countryside and historical sites. The project transcends the narrow focus on single Romantic author, analysing a big textual corpus digitally in addition to close reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My primary sources consist of a representative corpus of English and German Romantic texts including canonical works but also texts by women, minority and non-canonical authors. The most popular genres of Romanticism were novel and lyric poetry; but also essays, biographies, literary criticism, travelogues and historiography are included in the corpus. The metadata abstracted from correspondence is used to build another database to enable comparison between fictive and actual geographic maps of Romantic spatiality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project focuses thematically on the destabilisation of the centre-periphery distinction during the Romanticism and it has three main objectives. First, building a database of place names mentioned in the primary sources and visualise them on historical maps. I will apply existing geoparsing algorithms and also write a new Python programme called Strabo for this. The resulting database will be then published as an interactive website open for other scholars and general public. The second objective is to develop a research methodology for classifying place names and embedding geographical locations with emotional and cognitive judgements. The aim of this objective is to avoid the reduction of the lived space to a Cartesian coordinate grid, typical of the spatial humanities projects. The third objective is using the spatial database as a heuristic device for finding the relevant text passages for close reading.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A System for Identifying and Exploring Text Repetition in Large Historical Document Corpora</title>
      <link>/fi/publication/system/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/fi/publication/system/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applying BLAST to Text Reuse Detection in Finnish Newspapers and Journals, 1771–1910</title>
      <link>/fi/publication/blast/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/fi/publication/blast/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COMHIS</title>
      <link>/fi/project/comhis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/fi/project/comhis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Travelling Notions of Culture</title>
      <link>/fi/project/travelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/fi/project/travelling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
