<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks on Asko Nivala</title>
    <link>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks on Asko Nivala</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Asko Nivala</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://askonivala.github.io/talk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Romantic Cartographies</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/nulab-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2019 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/nulab-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Romantic Cartographies: Georeading Spatial Elements from Romantic Texts</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/nassr-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2019 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/nassr-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Romantic Cartographies: Georeading Spatial Elements from Romantic Texts</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/icr-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2019 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/icr-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In the Extreme Arctic Wilderness: Polar Regions in Romanticism</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/tromssa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/tromssa/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oceanic Exchanges: Tracing Global Information Networks In Historical Newspaper Repositories, 1840-1914</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/dhn-ocex-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 12:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/dhn-ocex-2018/</guid>
      <description>Poster at DHN 2018 conference
Presenters: Hannu Salmi, Asko Nivala, Mila Oiva, Otto Latva – Cultural History, University of Turku
Oceanic Exchanges: Tracing Global Information Networks in Historical Newspaper Repositories, 1840-1914 (OcEx) is a Digging into Data – Transatlantic Platform funded international and interdisciplinary project with a focus on studying spreading of news globally in the nineteenth century newspapers. The project combines digitized newspapers from Europe, US, Mexico, Australia, New Zealand, and the British and Dutch colonies of that time all over the world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metadata Analysis and Text Reuse Detection: Reassessing public discourse in Finland through newspapers and journals 1771–1917</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/dhn-comhis-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/dhn-comhis-2018/</guid>
      <description>Poster at DHN 2018 conference
Presenters: Ginter, Filip (1); Kanner, Antti (2); Lahti, Leo (1); Marjanen, Jani (2); Mäkelä, Eetu (2); Nivala, Asko (1); Rantala, Heli (1); Salmi, Hannu (1); Sippola, Reetta (1); Tolonen, Mikko (2); Vaara, Ville (2); Vesanto, Aleksi (2)
Organisation(s): 1: University of Turku; 2: University of Helsinki
During the period 1771–1917 newspapers developed as a mass medium in the Grand Duchy of Finland. This happened within two different imperial configurations (Sweden until 1809 and Russia 1809–1917) and in two main languages – Swedish and Finnish.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Redefinition of European Borders in English and German Romanticism</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/sks/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/sks/</guid>
      <description>Most texts are spatial implying a network of important places. This was especially typical of the Romantic era (1790–1840) that was characterised by the growing interest in historical and natural sites. My research project provides a new interpretation of English and German Romanticism by changing the focus from temporal to spatial. On the special focus of this presentation is Romantic Philhellenism and the interest in the Greek areas of the Ottoman Empire.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friedrich Schlegel and Ancient Greece as the Golden Age</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/athens/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/athens/</guid>
      <description>The nineteenth-century Romantic understanding of history is often confused with the longing for the past Golden Age. In this paper — that is based on my forth-coming monograph The Romantic Idea of the Golden Age in Friedrich Schlegel’s Philosophy of History (New York: Routledge 2017) — the problem of the Golden Age is seen from a new angle by discussing it in the context of Friedrich Schlegel’s studies on ancient Greece.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Of Mice and Machines: Posthumanist Reading of E. T. A. Hoffmann&#39;s Nutcracker and the Mouse King</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/colorado/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/colorado/</guid>
      <description>E. T. A. Hoffmann’s “Nutcracker and the Mouse King” (“Nussknacker und Mausekönig”, 1816) is among the most read Romantic fairy tales. Despite, its automaton motif has not been discussed a lot. My paper provides a posthumanist reading of the text in comparison with “The Sandman” (“Der Sandman”, 1817) that includes the famous female automaton Olimpia. As the title suggests, “Nutcracker and the Mouse King” juxtaposes the machine with the organism. The story happens on the Christmas, when two children, Marie and Fritz, are waiting for their presents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Romantic Anthropocene? The Nonhuman Agency of the Polar Regions in Romanticism</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/geneva/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/talk/geneva/</guid>
      <description>I delivered a paper “The Romantic Anthropocene? The Nonhuman Agency of the Polar Regions in Romanticism” in Encountering Materiality: Science, Art, Language conference in Geneva, 23 – 25 June.
The special focus of my talk was Mary Shelley’s Frankenstein, and many key scenes of the novel are located in Geneva. Even the conference venue was very close to the Plainpalais, where Victor Frankenstein’s brother, William, is murdered in the novel. There is now a bronze statue of the Creature in the murder place and he is looking towards the Salève, where he will hide after his deed.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>