<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks on Asko Nivala</title>
    <link>/talk/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks on Asko Nivala</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Asko Nivala</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/talk/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>In the Extreme Arctic Wilderness: Polar Regions in Romanticism</title>
      <link>/talk/tromssa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/tromssa/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oceanic Exchanges: Tracing Global Information Networks In Historical Newspaper Repositories, 1840-1914</title>
      <link>/talk/dhn-ocex-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 12:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/dhn-ocex-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Poster at DHN 2018 conference&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presenters: Hannu Salmi, Asko Nivala, Mila Oiva, Otto Latva – Cultural History, University of Turku&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oceanic Exchanges: Tracing Global Information Networks in Historical Newspaper Repositories, 1840-1914&lt;/em&gt; (OcEx) is a &lt;em&gt;Digging into
Data – Transatlantic Platform&lt;/em&gt; funded international and interdisciplinary project with a focus on studying spreading of news globally
in the nineteenth century newspapers. The project combines digitized newspapers from Europe, US, Mexico, Australia, New Zealand, and
the British and Dutch colonies of that time all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project examines patterns of information flow, spread of text reuse, and global conceptual changes across national, cultural and
linguistic boundaries in the nineteenth century newspapers. The project links the different newspaper corpora, scattered into
different national libraries and collections using various kinds of metadata and printed in several languages, into one whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research group members come from Finland, the US, the Netherlands, Germany, Mexico, and UK. OcEx’s participating institutions are
Loughborough University, Northeastern University, North Carolina State University, Universität Stuttgart, Universidad Nacional
Autónoma de México, University College London, University of Nebraska-Lincoln, University of Turku, and Utrecht University. The
project’s 90 million newspaper pages come from Australia&amp;rsquo;s Trove Newspapers, the British Newspapers Archive, Chronicling America
(US), Europeana Newspapers, Hemeroteca Nacional Digital de México, National Library of Finland, National Library of the Netherlands
(KB), the National Library of Wales, New Zealand’s PapersPast, and a strategic collaboration with Cengage Publishing, one of the
leading commercial custodians of digitized newspapers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metadata Analysis and Text Reuse Detection: Reassessing public discourse in Finland through newspapers and journals 1771–1917</title>
      <link>/talk/dhn-comhis-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/dhn-comhis-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Poster at DHN 2018 conference&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presenters: Ginter, Filip (1); Kanner, Antti (2); Lahti, Leo (1); Marjanen, Jani (2); Mäkelä, Eetu (2); Nivala, Asko (1); Rantala, Heli (1); Salmi, Hannu (1); Sippola, Reetta (1); Tolonen, Mikko (2); Vaara, Ville (2); Vesanto, Aleksi (2)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organisation(s): 1: University of Turku; 2: University of Helsinki&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the period 1771–1917 newspapers developed as a mass medium in the Grand Duchy of Finland. This happened within two different imperial configurations (Sweden until 1809 and Russia 1809–1917) and in two main languages – Swedish and Finnish. &lt;em&gt;The Computational History and the Transformation of Public Discourse in Finland, 1640–1910&lt;/em&gt; (COMHIS) project studies the transformation of public discourse in Europe and in Finland via an innovative combination of original data, state-of-the-art quantitative methods that have not been previously applied in this context, and an open source collaboration model.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Redefinition of European Borders in English and German Romanticism</title>
      <link>/talk/sks/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/sks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most texts are spatial implying a network of important places. This was especially typical of the Romantic era (1790–1840) that was characterised by the growing interest in historical and natural sites. My research project provides a new interpretation of English and German Romanticism by changing the focus from temporal to spatial. On the special focus of this presentation is Romantic Philhellenism and the interest in the Greek areas of the Ottoman Empire. The Napoleonic Wars (1803–1815) and the Greek War of Independence (1821–1829) were redefining the borders of Europe, and the English and German Romantics were actively participating on the spatial definition of European culture. I analyse the spatiality of Romantic texts by reconstructing the various maps they implied by using named-entity recognition (NER), geoparsing and other text mining methods. The study of Romanticism has often focused on the canon of few famous authors, but applying the methods of the digital humanities has a potential to analyse a much bigger corpus of primary sources.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friedrich Schlegel and Ancient Greece as the Golden Age</title>
      <link>/talk/athens/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/athens/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The nineteenth-century Romantic understanding of history is often confused with the longing for the past Golden Age. In this paper — that is based on my forth-coming monograph &lt;em&gt;The Romantic Idea of the Golden Age in Friedrich Schlegel’s Philosophy of History&lt;/em&gt; (New York: Routledge 2017) — the problem of the Golden Age is seen from a new angle by discussing it in the context of Friedrich Schlegel’s studies on ancient Greece. Interestingly, Schlegel argued that Hesiod’s myth of a past Golden Age in the beginning of history was itself a product of antiquity, imagined without any historical ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By making a distinction between ‘the Golden Age’ and ‘the age of blossoming’ (Blütezeit) the paper shows that Schlegel was not a primitivist and he was in fact very skeptical about the Golden Age in the beginning of time. Schlegel compared the history of antiquity with the growth of a plant, seeing the highest phase of Greek civilization in Attic culture (rather than in the ‘savage’ world of Homer’s epics), and its final urban stage in Alexandria represented decay. The status of ancient Athens was, in Schlegel’s view, the fullest flowering of Western civilization. In contrast to Winckelmann’s studies on sculpture, Schlegel located the core of the Greek cultivation in its institution of the theatre. Attic tragedy, and more specifically Sophocles, represented the apogee of the natural cultivation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Of Mice and Machines: Posthumanist Reading of E. T. A. Hoffmann&#39;s Nutcracker and the Mouse King</title>
      <link>/talk/colorado/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/colorado/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;E. T. A. Hoffmann’s “Nutcracker and the Mouse King” (“Nussknacker und Mausekönig”, 1816) is among the most read Romantic fairy tales. Despite, its automaton motif has not been discussed a lot. My paper provides a posthumanist reading of the text in comparison with “The Sandman” (“Der Sandman”, 1817) that includes the famous female automaton Olimpia. As the title suggests, “Nutcracker and the Mouse King” juxtaposes the machine with the organism. The story happens on the Christmas, when two children, Marie and Fritz, are waiting for their presents. The engineer Drosselmeyer gives them a mechanical castle, which is so immersive that Fritz tries to go inside its mechanism. However, children lose soon their interest in the castle, because it can only operate on the pregiven rules of the machinery. At the first glance, Hoffmann seems to juxtapose the mechanical castle with the free imagination of children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially interesting are the similarities between Marie’s godfather Drosselmeier and Coppelius in “The Sandman”: both are engineers of automata. One of the most horrible scenes in “The Sandman” is Coppelius disassembling Nathanael’s body. Although “Nutcracker and the Mouse King” is a fairy tale, also Drosselmeier restructures Princess Pirlipat’s body like an automaton: “He took Princess Pirlipat very carefully to pieces, screwed off her hands and her feet, and examined her interior structure.” In a posthumanist way, “The Nutcracker and the Mouse King” questions any simple boundary between an animal and a machine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Romantic Anthropocene? The Nonhuman Agency of the Polar Regions in Romanticism</title>
      <link>/talk/geneva/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/geneva/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I delivered a paper “The Romantic Anthropocene? The Nonhuman Agency of the Polar Regions in Romanticism” in &lt;em&gt;Encountering Materiality: Science, Art, Language&lt;/em&gt; conference in Geneva, 23 – 25 June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/frankenstein.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Frankenstein&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The special focus of my talk was Mary Shelley’s Frankenstein, and many key scenes of the novel are located in Geneva. Even the conference venue was very close to the Plainpalais, where Victor Frankenstein’s brother, William, is murdered in the novel. There is now a bronze statue of the Creature in the murder place and he is looking towards the Salève, where he will hide after his deed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
