<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Asko Nivala</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Asko Nivala</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Asko Nivala</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Romantic Cartographies</title>
      <link>/project/cartography/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/cartography/</guid>
      <description>Romantic Cartographies: Lived and Imagined Space in English and German Romantic Texts, 1790–1840 Most texts are spatial implying a network of important places. This was especially typical of the Romantic era (1790–1840) that was characterised by the growing interest in historical and natural sites. My postdoctoral research project provides a new interpretation of English and German Romanticism by changing the focus from temporal to spatial. I analyse the spatiality of Romantic texts by reconstructing the various geographic maps they implied.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friedrich Schlegel&#39;s Philosophy of History (2007—2015)</title>
      <link>/project/schlegel/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/schlegel/</guid>
      <description>I defended my doctoral dissertation in 2015. It discussed the themes of the Golden Age and the Kingdom of God in Friedrich Schlegel’s (1772–1829) early thought. The project was funded by the Finnish Cultural Foundation and the Oskar Öflund Foundation. In the final stages of the research work, I was also working in the Travelling Notions of Culture project, funded by the Academy of Finland.
A monograph based on my PhD dissertation was published in February 2017 with the title The Romantic Idea of the Golden Age in Friedrich Schlegel’s Philosophy of History.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COMHIS</title>
      <link>/project/comhis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/comhis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Travelling Notions of Culture</title>
      <link>/project/travelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/travelling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>