<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>5 on Asko Nivala</title>
    <link>/publication_types/5/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 5 on Asko Nivala</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Asko Nivala</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/publication_types/5/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Romantic Idea of the Golden Age in Friedrich Schlegel&#39;s Philosophy of History</title>
      <link>/publication/schlegel-monograph/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/schlegel-monograph/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Asko Nivalas Arbeit ist von Bedeutung für die Friedrich-Schlegel-Forschung aufgrund ihrer neuen Einsichten in ein zentrales Konzept seiner Geschichtsphilosophie. Sie überzeugt durch ihren Mut zur Komplexität. Zugleich liegt ein Verdienst der Dissertation darin, der englischsprachigen Forschung eine Einführung in Schlegels Denken zu bieten. Das leistet die Arbeit durch den Ausweis von Anknüpfungspunkten an aktuelle theoretische Diskurse (›posthumanism‹, ›ecocriticism‹, ›primitivism‹) auf der einen Seite und auf der anderen durch ein hohes Reflexionsniveau hinsichtlich der Übersetzung zentraler Termini Schlegels ins Englische.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Travelling Notions of Culture in Early Nineteenth-Century Europe</title>
      <link>/publication/travelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/travelling/</guid>
      <description>Topic The chapters of this volume concentrate on the following themes: What were the sites of culture, civilization and Bildung and how were these sites employed in defining these concepts? What kind of borders did this process of definition and its inherent spatial imagination produce? What were the connecting routes between the supposed centers and peripheries? What were the strategies of envisioning, negotiating and transforming cultural territories in early nineteenth-century Europe?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7 for the Price of 1</title>
      <link>/publication/7for1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/7for1/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>