<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on Asko Nivala</title>
    <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on Asko Nivala</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Asko Nivala</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/publication/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Schillers Geschichtsdenken: Die Unbegreiflichkeit der Weltgeschichte by Alexander Jakovljević (review)</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/schiller/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/schiller/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In lieu of an abstract, here is a brief excerpt of the content:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asko Nivala&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander Jakovljević. Schillers Geschichtsdenken: Die Unbegreiflichkeit der Weltgeschichte. Berlin: Ripperger &amp;amp; Kremers Verlag, 2015. 381 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the many contributions of Immanuel Kant&amp;rsquo;s Critique of Judgment (1790) was to question the dogmatic belief in providence: Kant argued that the human mind represents both organic nature and human history as if (als ob) both were teleological, although we can never verify this claim. Despite the fact that Kant limited teleology to regulative use, Karl Löwith claimed in his influential study Meaning in History (1949) that the nineteenth-century philosophy of history is nothing but secularized eschatology. Although Löwith&amp;rsquo;s argument is a simplification, his criticism of master narratives had enormous influence on the development of postmodernism. Since Hayden White&amp;rsquo;s Metahistory (1973), historians have debated to what extent historical events themselves have order and to what extent it is only the historian&amp;rsquo;s narration that gives them meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander Jakovljević&amp;rsquo;s Schillers Geschichtsdenken: Die Unbegreiflichkeit der Weltgeschichte (2015) shows how complex Friedrich Schiller&amp;rsquo;s historical thought was, and provides some new insights into how he theorized the relationship between teleology and contingency in history. Schiller&amp;rsquo;s place is very interesting among the post-Kantian philosophers, because he published his major works before the rise of German idealism: his position seems to be somewhere between Kant&amp;rsquo;s regulative approach to teleology and Hegel&amp;rsquo;s belief that the telos of history is the accumulation of freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jakovljević convincingly shows that Schiller&amp;rsquo;s position is based on the tension between two almost opposite views of history. In 1789, Schiller was appointed professor of history at the university of Jena on Goethe&amp;rsquo;s recommendation. His famous inaugural lecture Was heißt und zu welchem Ende studiert man Universalgeschichte? (1789) appears to be firmly anchored in the belief that human history is a teleological process. It was published one year before Kant&amp;rsquo;s criticism of teleological judgments in the third critique. In contrast, Ueber das Erhabene (1801) provides a very different understanding of history. Schiller argued there that history is incomprehensible and seems to be ruled more by coincidence (Zufall) than teleology. The previous scholarship has often assumed that Schiller moved from earlier providentialism to a more pessimist understanding of history because of his disappointment with the horrors of the French Revolution. According to Jakovljević, Schiller&amp;rsquo;s hovering between providentialism and coincidentalism should not be seen as a linear development from the former to the latter. Rather Jakovljević proposes that Schiller&amp;rsquo;s position becomes more understandable in a context of genre-specific readings that take into account all three fields in which Schiller was active: philosophy of history, historiography, and historical drama. In addition to the introduction (Chapter 1) and conclusions (Chapter 5), the book is divided into three chapters that follow this classification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The introduction is carefully written, and defines the key concepts of the study, namely telos, contingency (Kontingenz), and coincidence (Zufall), and explains the theoretical framework provided by Reinhart Koselleck and Hayden White. Chapter 2 starts with Schiller&amp;rsquo;s inaugural lecture, which again supported the idea that historical development is teleological. In a teleological framework every historical event must be necessary, but Schiller&amp;rsquo;s own work as a historian was in tension with this theoretical assumption of universal history. This problem became evident for Schiller especially when he was working with medieval [End Page 324] sources and the age of Crusades: it was difficult to explain why the Middle Ages were necessary for the universal development of mankind. Highlighting Schiller&amp;rsquo;s aesthetic approach to history, Jakovljević focuses on the metaphors Schiller used. For instance, describing medieval history as &amp;ldquo;unknown ocean&amp;rdquo; (ungewisses Meer) implies that historical events are coincidental. This difficulty was related to the premises of the Enlightenment, for the Middle Ages was still mostly seen as an era of religious fanaticism, political despotism, and a multitude of chaotic events resulting from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[The end of excerpt.]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review of Romanticism, Humanism, Judaism / Romantik, Humanismus, Judentum</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/eichner/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/eichner/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A System for Identifying and Exploring Text Repetition in Large Historical Document Corpora</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/system/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/system/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applying BLAST to Text Reuse Detection in Finnish Newspapers and Journals, 1771–1910</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/blast/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/blast/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Romantic Idea of the Golden Age in Friedrich Schlegel&#39;s Philosophy of History</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/schlegel-monograph/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/schlegel-monograph/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Asko Nivalas Arbeit ist von Bedeutung für die Friedrich-Schlegel-Forschung aufgrund ihrer neuen Einsichten in ein zentrales Konzept
seiner Geschichtsphilosophie. Sie überzeugt durch ihren Mut zur Komplexität. Zugleich liegt ein Verdienst der Dissertation darin, der
englischsprachigen Forschung eine Einführung in Schlegels Denken zu bieten. Das leistet die Arbeit durch den Ausweis von
Anknüpfungspunkten an aktuelle theoretische Diskurse (›posthumanism‹, ›ecocriticism‹, ›primitivism‹) auf der einen Seite und auf der
anderen durch ein hohes Reflexionsniveau hinsichtlich der Übersetzung zentraler Termini Schlegels ins Englische.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Elisa Ronzheimer, Athenäum – &lt;em&gt;Jahrbuch der Friedrich Schlegel-Gesellschaft&lt;/em&gt; 2017&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mediality and Intermediality in Friedrich Schlegel’s Early Romantic Thought</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/intermediality/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/intermediality/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Travelling Notions of Culture in Early Nineteenth-Century Europe</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/travelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/travelling/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;topic&#34;&gt;Topic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chapters of this volume concentrate on the following themes: What were the sites of culture, civilization and &lt;em&gt;Bildung&lt;/em&gt; and how were these sites employed in defining these concepts? What kind of borders did this process of definition and its inherent spatial imagination produce? What were the connecting routes between the supposed centers and peripheries? What were the strategies of envisioning, negotiating and transforming cultural territories in early nineteenth-century Europe?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book adds new perspectives on ways of approaching spatiality in history by investigating, for example: the decisive role of the French revolution, the persistent interest in classical civilization and its sites, emerging urbanism and the culture of the cities, the changing constellations between centers and peripheries and the colonial extensions, or transfigurations, of culture. It also pays attention to the spatiality of culture as a metaphor, but simultaneously emphasizes the production of space in an era of technological innovation and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;contents&#34;&gt;Contents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction (Asko Nivala, Hannu Salmi and Jukka Sarjala)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part I: &lt;em&gt;Bildung&lt;/em&gt;, Civilisation and Cultural Space

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1. Catastrophic Revolution and the Rise of Romantic &lt;em&gt;Bildung&lt;/em&gt; (Asko Nivala)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2. Classical Civilisation Confronts Modern Nationalism: Greek Colonies in Early Nineteenth-Century Scholarship (Janne Tunturi)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3. Between Nostalgia and Utopia: The Construction of Jewish Cultural Space in Early Nineteenth-Century Europe (Jakob Egholm Feldt and Cecilie S. Schrøder Simonsen)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part II: Centres and Borderlands

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4. The Colonial Displacement of Culture: Social Spaces and Boundaries in a Nineteenth-Century Diary from Greenland (Inge Seiding)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5. Nordic Travellers Between the Centres and Peripheries of Civilisation (Heli Rantala)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6. The Kalevala and the Cartography of Poetry and Knowledge (Juhana Saarelainen)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part III: Challenging Spatial Boundaries

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7. Viral Virtuosity and the Itineraries of Celebrity Culture (Hannu Salmi)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8. Charles Dickens and the &amp;ldquo;Vagabond Savage&amp;rdquo; (Adam Hansen)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9. Travelling Through Urban Space: The Romantic Imagination of E. T. A. Hoffmann (Jukka Sarjala)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Appendix: Further Reading&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Catastrophic Revolution and the Rise of Romantic Bildung</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/catastrophic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/catastrophic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7 for the Price of 1</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/7for1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/7for1/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
