<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on Asko Nivala</title>
    <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on Asko Nivala</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Asko Nivala</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/publication/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review of Romanticism, Humanism, Judaism / Romantik, Humanismus, Judentum</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/eichner/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/eichner/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A System for Identifying and Exploring Text Repetition in Large Historical Document Corpora</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/system/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/system/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applying BLAST to Text Reuse Detection in Finnish Newspapers and Journals, 1771–1910</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/blast/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/blast/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Romantic Idea of the Golden Age in Friedrich Schlegel&#39;s Philosophy of History</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/schlegel-monograph/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/schlegel-monograph/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Asko Nivalas Arbeit ist von Bedeutung für die Friedrich-Schlegel-Forschung aufgrund ihrer neuen Einsichten in ein zentrales Konzept
seiner Geschichtsphilosophie. Sie überzeugt durch ihren Mut zur Komplexität. Zugleich liegt ein Verdienst der Dissertation darin, der
englischsprachigen Forschung eine Einführung in Schlegels Denken zu bieten. Das leistet die Arbeit durch den Ausweis von
Anknüpfungspunkten an aktuelle theoretische Diskurse (›posthumanism‹, ›ecocriticism‹, ›primitivism‹) auf der einen Seite und auf der
anderen durch ein hohes Re exionsniveau hinsichtlich der Übersetzung zentraler Termini Schlegels ins Englische.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Elisa Ronzheimer, Athenäum – &lt;em&gt;Jahrbuch der Friedrich Schlegel-Gesellschaft&lt;/em&gt; 2017&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mediality and Intermediality in Friedrich Schlegel’s Early Romantic Thought</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/intermediality/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/intermediality/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Travelling Notions of Culture in Early Nineteenth-Century Europe</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/travelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/travelling/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;topic&#34;&gt;Topic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chapters of this volume concentrate on the following themes: What were the sites of culture, civilization and &lt;em&gt;Bildung&lt;/em&gt; and how were these sites employed in defining these concepts? What kind of borders did this process of definition and its inherent spatial imagination produce? What were the connecting routes between the supposed centers and peripheries? What were the strategies of envisioning, negotiating and transforming cultural territories in early nineteenth-century Europe?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book adds new perspectives on ways of approaching spatiality in history by investigating, for example: the decisive role of the French revolution, the persistent interest in classical civilization and its sites, emerging urbanism and the culture of the cities, the changing constellations between centers and peripheries and the colonial extensions, or transfigurations, of culture. It also pays attention to the spatiality of culture as a metaphor, but simultaneously emphasizes the production of space in an era of technological innovation and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;contents&#34;&gt;Contents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction (Asko Nivala, Hannu Salmi and Jukka Sarjala)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part I: &lt;em&gt;Bildung&lt;/em&gt;, Civilisation and Cultural Space

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1. Catastrophic Revolution and the Rise of Romantic &lt;em&gt;Bildung&lt;/em&gt; (Asko Nivala)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2. Classical Civilisation Confronts Modern Nationalism: Greek Colonies in Early Nineteenth-Century Scholarship (Janne Tunturi)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3. Between Nostalgia and Utopia: The Construction of Jewish Cultural Space in Early Nineteenth-Century Europe (Jakob Egholm Feldt and Cecilie S. Schrøder Simonsen)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part II: Centres and Borderlands

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4. The Colonial Displacement of Culture: Social Spaces and Boundaries in a Nineteenth-Century Diary from Greenland (Inge Seiding)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5. Nordic Travellers Between the Centres and Peripheries of Civilisation (Heli Rantala)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6. The Kalevala and the Cartography of Poetry and Knowledge (Juhana Saarelainen)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part III: Challenging Spatial Boundaries

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7. Viral Virtuosity and the Itineraries of Celebrity Culture (Hannu Salmi)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8. Charles Dickens and the &amp;ldquo;Vagabond Savage&amp;rdquo; (Adam Hansen)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9. Travelling Through Urban Space: The Romantic Imagination of E. T. A. Hoffmann (Jukka Sarjala)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Appendix: Further Reading&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Catastrophic Revolution and the Rise of Romantic Bildung</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/catastrophic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/catastrophic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7 for the Price of 1</title>
      <link>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/7for1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://askonivala.github.io/publication/7for1/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
